Guide to the Tamiment Library Web Collection on Organizations WEB.ARC.003
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
- Revolutionary Communist Party, USA Archived Website, Sep 23, 2007- ongoing; Revolutionary Communist Party, USA
  The Revolutionary Communist Party, USA is a Maoist organization inspired by the Chinese Cultural Revolution of the late 1960s-early 1970s. Its long-time leader is Bob Avakian. The website contains issues of their newspaper, Revolution, the Revolutionary Communist Party's platform, works and a biography of Avakian, and other publications and reports.
  Communism -- United States.; Maoism -- United States.; Avakian, Bob
- Revolutionary Workers Group Archived Website, May 2, 2011- ongoing; Revolutionary Workers Group
  A revolutionary socialist group based on the work of Marx, Engels, Lenin, Trotsky. The website contains their Speak Out Now broadside, their workplace newsletter, event listings, and other publications.
  Trotskyism -- United States.; Socialism -- United States.
- Rosenberg Fund for Children Archived Website, Nov 11, 2013- ongoing; Rosenberg Fund for Children
  The Rosenberg Fund for Children, established in 1990 by Robert Meeropol (son of Julius and Ethel Rosenberg), to aid the children of targeted activists that have participated in activities to preserve civil liberties, wage peace, safeguard the environment, combat racism and homophobia, and organize on behalf of workers, prisoners, immigrants and others. The website contains information on grant funding, news and events related to grantees, and information on the Rosenberg case.
  Rosenberg, Ethel, 1915-1953; Rosenberg, Julius, 1918-1953
- Seton Hall Law School - Guantanamo Reports Archived Website, Jul 9, 2009- ongoing; Seton Hall University. School of Law. Center for Social Justice
  Since 2006, Fellows with the Center for Policy and Research have been analyzing government data to illuminate the interrogations and intelligence practices of the United States. The findings have been quite revealing, showing that what's found in the data is often the best divulger of the truth. The reports have been introduced into the Congressional record by the Senate Armed Services Committee, the Senate Judiciary Committee, the House Armed Services Committee, and as part of a Resolution by the European Parliament.
  Iraq War, 2003-2011 |x Prisoners and prisons, American.; Lawyers -- Political activity -- United States.; Iraq War, 2003-2011 |x Law and legislation.; Guantánamo Bay Detention Camp
- Sex Worker's Outreach Project (New York Chapter) Archived Website, May 11, 2012- ongoing; Sex Worker's Outreach Project
  Sex Workers Outreach Project New York City (SWOP-NYC) and Sex Workers Action New yorK (SWANK) is an women's organization that works to improve the lives of current and former sex workers in New York City. SWOP-NYC projects include working on advocacy and policy campaigns, providing direct support to SWANK, event organizing, and other initiatives. The website contains meeting information, and news posts.
  Sex workers
- Sex Workers Project Archived Website, May 3, 2011- ongoing; Sex Workers Project (Urban Justice Center)
  The Sex Workers Project (SWP) provides legal services and training, and engages in documentation and policy advocacy for sex workers. Using a harm reduction and human rights model, the organization protects the rights and safety of sex workers who by choice, circumstance, or coercion remain in the industry. SWP provides information to policymakers, activists, and the media on the human rights abuses faced by sex workers and those who are at risk for engaging in sex work and use documentation-based advocacy, policy analysis, training and education, and collaboration with community-based service providers to advance practical, long-term solutions to the problems faced by sex workers.
- SocialDemocratsUSA.org Archived Website, Apr 9, 2009-Oct 13 2013; Social Democrats, U.S.A.
  Social Democrats USA (SDUSA) is a direct descendent of the Socialist Party USA., founded in 1972. The website archived is the website for the re-foundation of the party following the death of Penn Kemble in 2005. The organization was officially re-formed at a conference in 2009. Their aim was to form a center-left party that could win local elections. The website ceased to update in 2011.
- Socialist Action Archived Website, Apr 20, 2013- ongoing; Socialist Action
  Socialist Action is a national group of activists committed to the emancipation of workers and the oppressed. They work to revitalize the anti-war, labor, anti-racist, feminist, student and other social movements and bring activists together from different backgrounds into a revolutionary workers' party. Their ultimate goal is a truly democratic society. The website contains a detailed platform, news, pamphlets, and Marxist educational resources.
- Socialist Alternative Archived Website, Sep 1, 2009- ongoing; Socialist Alternative (U.S.)
  Socialist Alternative, founded in 1981, is a national organization that campaigns against United States two party system and advocates for a socialist alternative. They campaign for a mass workers party to represent the interests of workers, youth, and the environment. They advocate for a living wage for all; money for jobs and education, not war; environmental sustainability; equal rights for all; and socialism. Socialist Alternative is in political solidarity with the Committee for a Workers' International. The website publishes a newspaper, Socialist Alternative, and news on healthcare, US and world politics, the environment, and the workers movement.
- Socialist International Archived Website, May 4, 2012- ongoing; Socialist International (1951- )
  Socialist International, established in 1951 by the Frankfurt Congress, is the worldwide organization of social democratic, socialist and labour parties. It currently brings together 162 political parties and organizations from all continents. The website contains their constitution, committees, commission, congresses, and library. The homepage contains news updates on the organization.
  Socialism
- Socialist Labor Party of America Archived Website, Jul 26, 2009- ongoing; Socialist Labor Party
  The Socialist Labor Party (SLP) is the original party of socialism in America. Organized as the Workingmen's Party in 1876, the Party was renamed in 1877.Its longtime leader was Daniel De Leon (1852-1914), Marxist author and editor of The People, the SLP newspaper. As the only nationally organized party of socialism in America until 1900, the SLP attracted Socialists of all tendencies to its ranks. However, the Marxist element became dominant by 1890, when the Party was reorganized on a Marxist basis. The SLP has played a prominent role in the economic and political life of the United States. It ran the first socialist presidential campaign in 1892, and fielded national tickets in every presidential campaign through 1976. The SLP's goal is a classless society based on collective ownership and control of the industries and social services, these to be administered in the interests of all society through a Socialist Industrial Union government composed of democratically elected representatives from all the industries and services of the land. Production would be carried on for use instead of profit. The SLP program for achieving this revolutionary change from capitalism to socialism is based on the Marxist tenet that socialism can be achieved only through the classconscious action "of the working class itself." The Socialist Industrial Union program, as the SLP program is known, developed by Daniel De Leon (1852-1914), is a continuation of Karl Marx's ideas on a workers' government. In all essentials--political and economic classwide organization, the breakup of the state, workers' democracy, the seizure of social power by the organized producers and their socialist reorganization of the economy--the SIU program of the SLP conforms to the democratic premises underlying Marx's concept of socialism.
  Socialism -- United States.; De Leon, Daniel, 1852-1914
- Socialist Party of New York City Archived Website, Aug 10, 2009-Aug 14, 2014; Socialist Party of New York
  The website of the NYC Local of the Socialist Party USA. The website contains international and local news, event listings, and other multimedia.
  Socialism -- United States -- History -- 20th century
- Socialist Party USA Archived Website, Sep 23, 2007- ongoing; Socialist Party (U.S.)
  The Socialist Party USA, established 1973, is a descendant of the Socialist Party (U.S.), founded in 1901, and strives to establish a radical democracy that places people's lives under their own control and advocates for a non-racist, classless, feminist socialist society. The Socialist Party fights for progressive changes compatible with a socialist future. They support militant working class struggles and electoral action, independent of the capitalist controlled two-party system, to present socialist alternatives. The website contains more information on their platform, their party publication, The Socialist, event listings, organizing assistance, and electoral action.
- Socialist Party USA, 40th Anniversary of Reconstitution Archived Website, Jun 20, 2013-Jun 20, 2014; Socialist Party (U.S.)
  This website is the site for the 40th anniversary of the reconstitution of the Socialist Party USA in 2013. The website contains an anniversary journal, a short history of the organization, and some digitized historical documents.
- Socialist Party USA National Organizing Conference Archived Website, Sep 20, 2014-ongoing; Socialist Party (U.S.)
  This website contains information about the Socialist Party USA's annual organizing conference. The purpose of this event is to educate and train those who would like to know more about campaigning, issue and policy development, and organizing. The website contains information on workshops and travel information. In 2014, the conference took place in Chicago.
  Socialism; Conferences.
- Socialist Viewpoint Archived Website, Aug 16, 2009- ongoing; Socialist Viewpoint Publishing Association.
  The Socialist Viewpoint Publishing Association publishes Socialist Viewpoint in the interests of the working class. The editors take positions consistent with revolutionary Marxism. Socialist Viewpoint magazine has been edited and distributed by a group of revolutionaries who share a common political outlook stemming from the old Socialist Workers Party of James P. Cannon, and Socialist Action from 1984 through 1999.
- Soh Daiko Archived Website, Aug 26, 2014-ongoing; Soh Daiko (Musical group)
  Soh Daiko, founded in New York City in 1979, was the first group in the Northeastern United States. Taiko, a kind of traditional Japanese drumming used for ritual celebrations and festivals also became a contemporary performing art of mass drumming in the 1960s. Soh Daiko's performances blend movement and choreography with music; its repertoire includes traditional compositions from Shinto music tradition, adapting existing taiko compositions and performing original arrangements by its own members. The group has participated in local New York City cultural festivities, it has performed across the United States, Canada, and the United Kingdom, and has been featured in segments on public radio and television. The website contains event listings, videos of their performances, images, and information about recruitment.
  Musical instruments - Japan; Percussion ensembles.; Taiko (Drum ensemble)
- Solidarity-US.org Archived Website, Jun 21, 2011- ongoing; Solidarity (Organization: U.S.)
  Solidarity, founded in 1986, is an independent socialist organization dedicated to forming a broad regrouping of the U.S. left and publishes the periodical Against the Current. They oppose capitalism, advocate for reproductive rights, other feminist demands and an ecologically balanced society, support the struggles of gay, lesbian, bisexual and transgender activists, fight against US imperialism, and socialism. The website contains their platform, their webzine, and publications.
  Socialism -- United States.; Trotskyism -- United States.
- Spirit of Haymarket: Communist Party of Illinois Blog Archived Website, Aug 11, 2010- ongoing; Communist Party of the United States of America (Ill.)
  Spirit of Haymarket is the blog of the Communist Party of Illinois.
  Communism -- Illinois.
- Students for a Democratic Society Archived Website, Oct 4, 2007 - Feb 10, 2011; Students for a Democratic Society (U.S.)
  Students for a Democratic Society (SDS), founded in 2006, which takes its name from a similar earlier organization founded in 1962, is a radical, multi-issue student and youth organization working to build power in schools and communities. The SDS focuses on anti-war campaigns and other civil rights and social justice issues. The last capture for this site was February 2011. Their new website, http://www.newsds.org/, is being captured in the Education and Student Movements Web Archive.
  Student movements -- United States.; College students |x Political activity |z United States.
- Students for a Democratic Society Archived Website, Feb 26, 2010- ongoing; Students for a Democratic Society (U.S.)
  Students for a Democratic Society (SDS), founded in 2006, which takes its name from a similar earlier organization founded in 1962, is a radical, multi-issue student and youth organization working to build power in schools and communities. The SDS focuses on anti-war campaigns and other civil rights and social justice issues.
- Students for a New American Politics Archived Website, Feb 15, 2010- ongoing; Students for a New American Politics
  Students for a New American Politics (SNAP) is a student-run political action committee, founded in 2005. The mission of SNAP is to elect progressive candidates and train students to become progressive leaders in the future. The organization trains college students, recent graduates, and college-age youth to serve as SNAP Fellows, full-time field organizers for Congressional candidates.
  Political action committees |z United States.; Students -- Political activity -- United States.
- Students for Free Culture Archived Website, Jul 7, 2011-Jul 5, 2013; Students for Free Culture
  Students for Free Culture (SFC) is a non-partisan group of students and young people who work to get their peers involved in the free culture movement, a movement that promotes the freedom to distribute and modify creative works in the form of free content by using the Internet and other forms of media.. SFC chapters exist at over 40 colleges and universities around the world. Students for Free Culture was founded by two Swarthmore students after they sued voting-machine manufacturer Diebold for abusing copyright law in 2003. SFC has collaborated with Creative Commons, the Electronic Frontier Foundation, Public Knowledge, Downhill Battle, and other free software and media reform groups.
  Copyright; Student movements.; Freedom of information.
- Tamiment Library & Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives, New York University. Archived Website, May 7, 2008, Jul 27, 2009 - ongoing; Tamiment Library
  The Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives at New York University form a unique, internationally-known center for scholarly research on Labor and the Left. The primary focus is the complex relationship between trade unionism and progressive politics and how this evolved over time. Archival, print, photograph, film, and oral history collections describe the history of the labor movement and how it related to the broader struggle for economic, social, and political change. In 1977 the Robert F. Wagner Archives was established as a joint program of the New York City Central Labor Council and the Tamiment Library. The Wagner is the designated repository for the records of the Council's more than 200 member unions. Today the Library has an extraordinary research collection documenting the history of organized labor in New York and the workers who built the City. Tamiment has one of the finest research collections in the country documenting the history of radical politics: socialism, communism, anarchism, utopian experiments, the cultural left, the New Left, and the struggle for civil rights and civil liberties. It is the repository for the Archives of Irish America, the Abraham Lincoln Brigade Archives, and a growing Asian American labor collection.
- Teachers for a Just Contract Archived Website, May 4, 2011-Aug 2, 2012; Teachers for a Just Contract
  Teachers for a Just Contract is a New York City base organization that works to improve the working conditions of teachers by struggling for the vigorous enforcement of their collective bargaining agreement, particularly in relation to disciplinary actions, harassment and job security. In addition they work to fight school overcrowding and protect their professional autonomy.
  Teachers' unions -- New York (State) -- New York; Teachers' contracts -- United States.; United Federation of Teachers
- Tenants Political Action Committee Archived Website, Mar 3, 2012 - ongoing; Tenants Political Action Committee
  Tenants Political Action Committee is a PAC that helps preserve and protect affordable housing for tenants in New York. Tenants PAC endorses candidates who are strong supporters of tenants' rights and gives renters more power with elected officials. The website contains news, endorsements, campaigns, and event listings.
- Theater for the New City Archived Website, Oct 6, 2011- ongoing; Theater for the New City (New York, N.Y.)
  Theater for the New City, founded in 1971 and known familiarly as "TNC", is one of New York City's leading Off-Off-Broadway theaters, known for radical political plays and community commitment. Productions at TNC have won 43 Obie Awards and the Pulitzer Prize for Drama. TNC currently exists as a 4-theater complex in a 30,000-square-foot (2,800 m2) space located at 155 1st Avenue, in Manhattan's East Village.
  Theatrical companies |z New York (State) |z New York.
- Theatre of the Oppressed Archived Website, May 6, 2012-; Theatre of the Oppressed
  The International Theatre of the Oppressed, founded in 1971 by Augusto Boal in Brazil, is a theatre technique that uses theatre as means of promoting social and political change, through the use of audience participation. The website contains a listing of theater groups that use the technique, news, and a library.
  Theater -- Political aspects.
- The Fugs Archived Website, Jul 13, 2010- ongoing; Fugs (Musical group)
  The Fugs, a group of poet-musicians, was founded in New York City's East Village in early 1965 by Ed Sanders, Ken Weaver, and Tuli Kupferberg (1923-2010). The band is a folk rock group whose song lyrics were informed by an anti-authoritarian, anti-war, bohemian sensibility. They have performed and issued albums for the last 35 years. This website is the band's official webpage.
  Protest songs -- United States.; Folk-rock music |z New York (State) |z New York.; Beat generation -- New York (State) -- New York.
- The Groundswell Collective Archived Website, Nov 16, 2009-Feb 15, 2014; Groundswell Collective
  The Groundswell Collective, founded in 2006, is a loose affiliation of artists that work at the intersection of art and activism. The collective is interested in how art relates to social movements and to use of the creativity of the radical left to create an impact in society. The collective uses various different media and the website maintains a blog, catalogs art and runs an online store and barter network.
  Art -- Political aspects -- United States
- The Militant Archived Website, Jul 30, 2009- ongoing; Militant (New York, N.Y.)
  This site contains articles from the Militant newspaper, a socialist newsweekly published in the interests of working people. The Militant is associated with the Socialist Workers Party, a U.S. Trotskyist organization.
  Socialism -- United States -- Periodicals.; Trotskyism -- United States.; Militant (New York, N.Y.); Socialist Workers Party
- The Reporters Committee for Freedom of the Press Archived Website, Dec 5, 2011- ongoing; Reporters Committee for Freedom of the Press
  The Reporters Committee for Freedom of the Press (RCFP) is an American nonprofit organization, founded in 1970, that provides free legal assistance to and on behalf of journalists. A number of prominent journalists presently sit on the organization's steering committee, including Dan Rather, and Judy Woodruff and, prior to his death, Walter Cronkite. Its offices are located in Arlington, Virginia.The RCFP actively aids in defending reporters facing subpoenas and court orders to disclose the identity of confidential sources. The Reporters Committee is also involved in a variety of First Amendment, shield law, freedom of information, and other free speech activities, including state open records and meetings law compliance. The organization publishes a quarterly magazine, The News Media and The Law. In addition, the Reporters Committee files legal briefs on a variety of issues that affect a journalist's ability to gather and disseminate news and also maintains a 24-hour legal defense hotline for journalists and media lawyers.
  Freedom of the press |z United States
- The Situationist International Text Library Archived Website, Aug 16, 2009- ongoing; Internationale situationniste
  Situationist International Text Library is part of Nothingness.org, an anarchist and situationist website. The Library is an ongoing project of uploading pieces of Situationist-related literature. Entire books, lengthy articles, excerpts from the journals Potlatch and Internationale Situationniste, newspaper articles, and other files.
  Internationale situationniste.; Anarchism |v Sources.
- The Socialist Archived Website, Dec 1, 2013- ongoing; Socialist Party (U.S.)
  The Socialist magazine and website are published by members of the Socialist Party USA. The website contains information on the Socialist Party's platform, issues of the magazine, and articles.
  Socialists -- United States.; Socialism -- United States -- Periodicals.
- The Trials of The Scottsboro Boys Archived Website, Aug 23, 2009; University of Missouri--Kansas City. School of Law
  This website is an archive dedicated to the Trials of the Scottsboro Boys, which was a set of trials, convictions, reversals, and retrials of an alleged gang rape of two white girls by nine black teenagers on a Southern Railroad freight run on March 25, 1931. The results of the trial opened southern juries to blacks, exacerbated sectional strife, and divided America's political left.
  Scottsboro Trial, Scottsboro, Ala., 1931.; African Americans |x Civil rights |z Alabama.
- This Stops Today Archived Website, Dec 10, 2014-Ongoing; This Stops Today
  This Stops Today came together to respond to the Staten Island grand jury's failure to indict police officers in the killing of Eric Garner in 2014. The organization called for eleven days of action to reflect the eleven times Eric Garner told police officers "I can't breathe" before he died. This website includes listings of actions in New York City.
  Police brutality.; Grand jury |z United States.; New York (N.Y.).; Black power.
- TIME'S UP! NYC Direct Action Environmental Organization Archived Website, Oct 26, 2009 - ongoing; Time's Up (New York, N.Y.)
  Founded in 1987, TIME'S UP! is a New York City based direct-action environmental group that uses events and educational programs to promote a more sustainable, less toxic city. TIME'S UP! works to educate people about the environmental impact of everyday decisions, including transportation use and food purchasing. TIME'S UP! sponsors many ride events to promote cycling and a bike co-op program.